Guide to the Lucy Monroe Calhoun Family Photographs and Papers, 1886-1993 and undated, bulk 1911-1933 RL.11103
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Developing out paper and gelatin silver photographs, 1900-1941 and undated; 1
  - Presentation photographs Chinese box two, 1910-1939; 7
    - Mrs. C. F. Wang's garden, 1920s; 6.75 x 4.75 in. (Box 9, Folder 2, Print RL11103-P-583)
      王太太的花园
      Mrs. C. F. Wang's Garden
    - Nan Hai tea garden, 1920s; 6.75 x 4.75 in. (Box 9, Folder 2, Print RL11103-P-584)
      南海茶室及花园
    - Ying Tai, Nan Hai, 1920s; 6.75 x 4.75 in. (Box 9, Folder 2, Print RL11103-P-585)
      南海瀛台
      Nan Hai. The Ying Tai
      Peking. Nan Hai. Ying T'ai
    - Wan Shan Dian, Chung Hai (Zhong Hai), 1920s; 4.75 x 6.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 2, Print RL11103-P-586)
      中海，万善殿
      Peking. Wan Shan Tien in the Chung Hai
    - Tree near walkway, Pei Hai (Bei Hai), 1920s; 6.75 x 4.75 in. (Box 9, Folder 2, Print RL11103-P-587)
      北海，古树，石桥
    - Kites for sale in market, 1920s; 4.75 x 6.75 in. (Box 9, Folder 2, Print RL11103-P-588)
      Kite vendor
      Peking. Kite vendor
      positive of RL11103-N-005. Photograph has black border.
    - Jehol (Chengde), the park., 1920s; 4.75 x 6.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 2, Print RL11103-P-589)
      Je ho park
      Jehol. The park
      Copy of RL11103-P-283. Photograph has black border.
    - Jehol (Chengde), Hsien-kung, Xumi Fushou Temple, 1920s; 4.75 x 6.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 2, Print RL11103-P-590)
      Jehol. Hsia Kung
      Jehol. Hain-Kung
    - Jehol (Chengde), Dafo Temple (Puning Temple), 1920s; 4.75 x 6.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 2, Print RL11103-P-591)
      承德，大佛寺（普宁寺）
      Je ho. Ta-Fo-szu
      Jehol. Ta Fo Ssu
    - Nankow Pass. Sung (Song) Dynasty gate on the old caravan road, 1920s; 4.75 x 6.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 2, Print RL11103-P-592)
      南口城宋代城门
      Nan V'ou posi. Sung Dynasty Gate, old caravan road
      Peiking to Kalgan. Nankow Pass. Sung Dynasty gate on the old caravan road.
    - Yungang caves, Sculpture flanked by two smaller sculptures, 1920s; 4.75 x 6.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 3, Print RL11103-P-593)
      云冈石窟，中间坐像，两旁站立侍者像
      Tatung. Yung Kan caves
    - Yungang caves, large sculpture, 1920s; 4.75 x 6.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 3, Print RL11103-P-594)
      云冈石窟，大佛坐像
    - Yungang caves, temple interior, 1920s; 4.75 x 6.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 3, Print RL11103-P-595)
      大同，云冈石窟，寺庙内部
      Tatung. Temple Int.
      Tatung. Temple interior
    - Pagoda at Wu Tai Shan, 1920s; 4.75 x 6.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 3, Print RL11103-P-596)
      Wu T'ai Shan trip. Chu Yang Hsien.
      Shansi. Trip to Wu Tai Shan. Pagoda at Chu Yang Hsien.
      Version of RL11103-P-398. Photograph has black border.
    - Kite vendor with customers, 1920s; 6.5 x 4.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 3, Print RL11103-P-597)
    - Pei Hai (Bei Hai). Court of the Great Tree, 1920s; 4.5 x 6.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 3, Print RL11103-P-598)
      北海，院中古树
      Peking. Pei Hai. Court of the Great Tree
    - Bronze pagoda at Xiantong Temple, 1930s; 4.5 x 6.5 in (Box 9, Folder 3, Print RL11103-P-599)
      Wu T'ai. Hsien Tung Szu. Golden Pagoda.
      Shansi. Wu T'ai Shan. Golden pagoda at Hsien Tung Ssu.
      Version of RL11103-P-305. Photograph has black border.
    - Statue with aura, 1920s; 4.5 x 6.5 in (Box 9, Folder 3, Print RL11103-P-600)
      大同，寺庙内，大佛像
      Tan t'ung. temple int.
    - Hatamen Street. Selling Persimmons, 1920s; 6.5 x 4.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 3, Print RL11103-P-601)
      哈德门（崇文门）大街，卖柿子的摊子
      Peking. Hatamen Street. Selling Persimmons
    - Pagoda of Cishou Temple, Balizhuang, Beijing, 1920s; 4.5 x 6.5 in (Box 9, Folder 3, Print RL11103-P-602)
      八里庄慈寿寺塔
      Pa-li-chuan
      Peking. Pa Li Chuan
    - Altar of Heaven, photograph by Serge Vargassoff, 1920s; 6.5 x 4.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 4, Print RL11103-P-603)
      天坛，斯尔格·沃特加索夫拍摄
      Altar of Heaven, Serge Vargassoff Peking
    - On a level of the Circular Mound Altar, 1920s; 6.75 x 4.75 in. (Box 9, Folder 4, Print RL11103-P-604)
      T'ien tan
      Copy of RL11103-P-237. Photograph has black border.
    - Gate of Supreme Harmony, 1920s; 6.75 x 4.75 in. (Box 9, Folder 4, Print RL11103-P-605)
      Forb. City
      Peking. The Forbidden City.
      Version of RL11103-P-109. Photograph has black border.
    - Decorative screen., 1920s; 4.75 x 6.75 in. (Box 9, Folder 4, Print RL11103-P-606)
      Version of RL11103-P-059.1. Photograph has black border.
    - Buddaist Sculpture, North end of gallery?, 1920s; 4.75 x 6.75 in. (Box 9, Folder 4, Print RL11103-P-607)
      Version of RL11103-P-061.1. Photograph has black border.
    - Tree and plantings in courtyard, 1920s; 4.75 x 6.75 in. (Box 9, Folder 4, Print RL11103-P-608)
      Version of RL11103-P-022.1. Photograph has black border.
    - Plantings in courtyard, 1920s; 4.75 x 6.75 in. (Box 9, Folder 4, Print RL11103-P-609)
    - Huo Shen Miao. Chinese New Year, 1920s; 4.75 x 6.75 in. (Box 9, Folder 4, Print RL11103-P-610)
      火神庙，春节
      Peking. Ho Shen Miao. Chinese New Year.
    - Hatamen Street. Persimmons vendor, 1920s; 6.5 x 4.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 4, Print RL11103-P-611)
      Ha-ta-men Ta-chich
      Hatamen Street. Persimmons vendor
    - Jehol (Chengde), (Yongyou Temple pagoda), 1920s; 6.5 x 4.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 4, Print RL11103-P-612)
      永佑寺舍利塔
      Jehol Park
      Version of RL11103-P-279. Photograph has black border.
    - Jehol (Chengde). Xumi Fuoshou Temple, Golden roofs, 1920s; 6.5 x 4.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 4, Print RL11103-P-613)
      承德，须弥福寿之庙，金瓦殿金色屋顶
      Je-ho. Hsin kung
      Jehol. Hsin-kung-golden roofs
    - Yungang Caves, Support structure, 1920s; 4.75 x 6.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 5, Print RL11103-P-614)
      大同，云冈石窟，石柱
      Ta-t'ung, Yung-Kan caves
    - Tatung. Porcelain screen, 1920s; 6.5 x 4.75 in. (Box 9, Folder 5, Print RL11103-P-615)
      大同九龙壁
      Ta-t'ung. Porcelain screen
      Tatung. Porcelain screen
    - Trip to Wu Tai Shan. Pagoda at Ting Hsien(Ding Xian), 1920s; 4.75 x 6.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 5, Print RL11103-P-616)
      前往五台山途中，河北定县开元寺塔
      Wu Tai Shan trip. Ting Hsien.
      Shansi. Trip to Wu Tai Shan. Pagoda at Ting Hsien.
    - Golden Water, 1920s; 6.75 x 4.75 in. (Box 9, Folder 5, Print RL11103-P-617)
      Peking. The Forbidden City
      Version of RL11103-P-107. Photograph has black border.
    - The Forbidden City. Sheng Wu Men gate with the palace guard, 1920s; 4.75 x 6.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 5, Print RL11103-P-618)
      紫禁城，神武门，站岗的侍卫们
      Sheng Wu Men
      Peking. The Forbidden City. Sheng Wu Men with the palace guard.
    - Nan Hai. The Ying T'ai (Ying Tai) from a distance., 1920s; 6.75 x 4.75 in. (Box 9, Folder 5, Print RL11103-P-619)
      南海，瀛台远观，
    - Jehol (Chengde). Pule temple, Xuguang Hall, 1920s; 4.75 x 6.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 5, Print RL11103-P-620)
      承德，普乐寺，旭光阁
      Je-ho. Yellow Temple
      Jehol. The Yellow temple
    - Ta Chuch Ssu (Dajue Temple). The pool., 1920s; 6.5 x 4.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 5, Print RL11103-P-621)
      西山大觉寺，池水
      Ta Chuch Ssu. The pool.
      Peking. Ta Chuch Ssu.
    - Coal Hill Temple deer, 1920s; 4.75 x 6.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 5, Print RL11103-P-622)
      煤山（景山）寿皇殿，铜鹿
      "Coal Hill"
    - Pei Hai (Bei Hai) tree and outbuilding, 1920s; 4.75 x 6.5 in. (Box 9, Folder 2, Print RL11103-P-623)
      北海，古树，亭子
      Peking. Pei Hai. Round City
- Chinese presentation photograph boxes, 1930s
  - Chinese presentation photograph box one (Box 5)
  - Chinese presentation photograph box two (Box 10)
- Albumen print photograph album, 1911
  The photograph album (60 pages) contains 94 albumen prints featuring images taken during the Calhoun party's travel between China and the United States in 1911, via Siberia. The back of the album contains a handwritten itinerary including identification of people in the photographs. Among the places photographed are Peiking (Beijing); Moscow; Berlin; Marken Island; Stratford-upon-Avon and Huntingdon, England; New York; Chicago; and Paris. The photographer for individual photographs is unclear. The album has suffered damage from chewing rodents and the leather cover is deteriorating. A separate list of photograph locations is included with the album.
  - Photograph album (Box 6)
- Lucy Monroe Calhoun papers, 1910-1950 and undated
  Series features primarily Lucy Monroe Calhoun's writings, including her 276-page memoir of her life in Peking from 1911-1912 and 1921-1936, as well as five typescript articles (some of which were later published) describing Peking, travel to Jehol, the Western Hills, and her house, along with a piece entitled "My Greatest Adventure was China." There are also seven letters by Calhoun to family members, with other assorted papers; postcards of 1930 Budapest; and a few pieces of printed material.
  - Memoir and photograph, 1936 and undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
    Contains Lucy Monroe Calhoun's 1936 memoir (276 pages, with forward, text, plus lists of photographs) of her life in China, primarily between 1910-1912, but also 1921-1936. She describes Peiking itself, as well as life and activities related to living in the American Legation, including dinners, entertainments, and extensive travel members participated in. Politics in China is also a major topic, especially the establishment of the Republic and the resulting change in status for the Manchu class and the Emperor. Other topics include servants, merchants and shopping, weddings, funerals, Chinese New Year, worship, and the temple house where she resided after 1921.
    The undated albumen photograph features Polly Root Collier, John Wellborn Root and Ellen Root, her parents, and her husband, Edward Maverick Collier.
  - Writings, 1950 and undated (Box 7)
    Five typescript articles written by Lucy Calhoun on Chinese topics, often with lists of photographs, all undated. Includes "Jehol by Mule-litter" (28 pages), "My Chinese House" (15 pages), untitled [on Peking] (16 pages), "The Western Hills" (31 pages), and "My Greatest Adventure was China" (27 pages), which is accompanied by a 2-page letter from an editor of the piece. The articles generally feature manuscript edits.
  - Papers, 1910-1945 and undated (Box 7)
    Includes 19 items, dated 1910-1945 and undated. There are seven letters from Lucy Calhoun to family members, mostly describing trips taken Peking, work and assistants for the Minister, dinner parties and other events planned, including reading habits and items read at a meeting of the Purple Cows, and making requests, especially that her niece, Polly Root Collier, be able to remain in China. Lucy wrote one letter from Paris in 1927, discussing Charles Lindbergh's popularity and her travel plans for return to China. There are also four letters written by a New York museum curator to Lucy, dated 1943-1945 and undated. He had been a fellow resident and friend to her in China, and in the letters he discusses his exhibitions, the war, and his desire to return to China. Other items include a bakery bill for Mrs. Russell in the American Legation, 1911; two telegrams 1911-1912; two envelopes, and an undated list of wedding presents. There are also three papers featuring Chinese characters; one of the items is identified in handwritten English as a calling card for a Mongol prince.
  - Postcards, 1912-1930 and undated; 4 folders (Box 7)
    Includes an accordion case containing 12 commercial postcards of Budapest, dated 1930, with images of the parliament buildings, the Royal Castle, bridges, and the railway station, among others. There are also 13 undated postcards of China, including images of the Temple of Heaven and the Marco Polo bridge, with other locations unidentified. Seven undated postcards of France feature the William the Conqueror Hostel. There are also 16 postcards of Japan dated 1912, featuring images around Nikko, with an additional 8 undated postcards containing images of Kasuga Jinjya.
  - Printed matter, 1911 and undated (Box 7)
    Includes three printed items: a program for a musical event at the American Legation in 1911, a description for a Buddha for Todaiji Temple in Japan, and an article on Lucy's House, published in German.
- Monroe Family papers, 1886-1962, 1993 and undated
  Series features primarily writings by Monroe family members, from letters to autobiographical and biographical pieces, along with some photographs, postcards, and a few newspaper clippings. Writings include letters by Polly Root Collier and Henry Stanton Monoe, Lucy Monroe Calhoun's niece and nephew, both of whom wrote extensive letters to family members during their stays with Calhoun in China, in 1911-1912 and 1933, respectively. These letters feature many of the same topics Calhoun covered in her memoir. Polly also wrote extensive letters regarding her own travels between 1953 and 1962. In addition, there are letters and an autobiography by William Stanton Monroe, mostly focusing on his business career, as well as a two letters by the patriarch of the family, Henry Stanton Monroe (1826-1903), written during his trip aboard a Cunard steamship in 1886. Anna Hammill Monroe wrote a biography of her son, Ernst Hamill Monroe, who died as a child. There is also a World War II letter written by Captain John Magruder, whose relationship to the Monroe family is unclear.
  - Polly Root Collier letters, 1911-1912, 1953-1962, 1993 and undated; 4 folders (Box 8)
    The earliest letters by Mary Louise "Polly" Root Collier date from her stay with her Aunt and Uncle, Lucy and William Calhoun, in China during 1911-1912. The 63 letters (with one albumen group photograph) were primarily written to her mother. They describe her travel to Peking, as well as activities and life in the American Legation in Peiking. [They also closely second Lucy Monroe Calhoun's topics in her memoir.] Among the topics are sightseeing parties, meetings of the Purple Cows, and the political unrest of the period. Collier includes a hand-drawn map of Peking and the Legation Quarter. In addition, Collier outlines her travel to Tsing Tau, Shanghai, and Manila, Philippines.
    Between 1953-1962 and undated, Collier wrote about 32 letters to a group of relatives," The Ranchers", who might have resided at White Gates Farm in Wayne, Illinois. Collier served on the Unitarian Service Committee's American Education Mission in Seoul, South Korea, between January and June 1954. Collier described her sightseeing and investigating community projects in several countries before reaching Seoul, including Hong Kong; Bangkok, Thailand; and Rangoon, Burma; along with several stops in India. Her letters from Seoul focus on her work, describing the territory, people, schools, children's games, and clothing, along with general conditions. Letters following her stay in Seoul generally provide detailed accounts of her travels, primarily in Europe, but in the Middle East and Asia as well. She describes her sightseeing trips, those she met, her forms of travel, along with general conditions in each country. One letter features a note in another hand, dated 1993.
  - Henry S. Monroe letters, 1933, 1973 and undated (Box 8)
    Henry S. Monroe wrote eighteen, often lengthy, letters to his parents, describing his travel to Peking, his stay with his Aunt Lucy, their activities and visitors, and visits to tourist attractions in Peking and beyond. He often mentions his taking photographs or filming events, along with his participation in plays. A background to the letters is the potential for invasion by the Japanese. In one letter he provides a romanized Chinese pronounciation guide. Includes his letter dated 1973 regarding William J. Calhoun's business background.
  - William S. Monroe autobiography and letters, 1943-1946 and undated (Box 8)
    Contains William S. Monroe's undate 17-page typescript autobiography, along with two unrelated personal letters he wrote in 1943 and 1946.
  - Henry Stanton Monroe (1826-1903) letters, 1886, 1953 (Box 8)
    Comprises two letters Henry Stanton Monroe wrote to his wife and children from the Cunard steamship "Servia," which was traveling in the North Atlantic in July and August 1886. Monroe describes his activities on board, including meals, walks, sitting on deck, as well as the ship itself. He also records the weather, and discusses his fellow passengers and their entertainments, including board and card games, betting, music, reading, and "athletic games." He mentions a call for a mock trial in which he is to participate, and describes the burial at sea of a child who died on board. There is an additional letter to Polly Root Collier regarding her request to include the letters in the Newberry Library's holdings.
  - Anna Hamill Monroe biography of Ernst Hamill Monroe, undated (Box 8)
    Anna Hamill Monroe wrote this undated, 42-page, typescript biography of her son, Ernst Hamill Monroe (1899-1904).
  - Captain John Magruder WWII letter, 1944 July 14 and undated (Box 8)
    Includes a typescript letter Captain Magruder wrote to his mother from Saipan, Marianas, where he was stationed. Magruder discussed fighting tactics used by American and Japanese forces. The letter was published in "The Parker Weekly;" a copy of the published version is inlcuded. It is unclear how this letter is related to the Monroe family.
  - Polly Root Collier photographs and postcards, 1888-1954 and undated (Box 8)
    Polly Root Collier's collection of 26 photographs, 1 cabinet card, 1 photo postcard, and 3 postcards, featuring images taken of Collier and others, as well as landscapes, in Peking, China; Manila, Phillippines; and Seoul, South Korea. There are also two group photographs from family gatherings in the United States. Includes one 3/4-portrait of Lucy Monroe Calhoun. The majority of the photographs and postcards have captions in ink or pencil on the back. There are also 19 negatives.
  - William S. Monroe? portrait, undated (Box 8)
    Albumen black-and-white portrait of possibly William S. Monroe seated at a piano. Photography studio is J. D. Toloff of Evansville, Ill.
  - Society page articles, 1941, 1946 (Box 8)
    Comprises two newspaper articles on New Year's Day parties held by the Monroe family in 1941 and 1946. One article is from the Chicago Tribune, the other is unattributed.